<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A trewe mirrour or glase wherin we maye beholde the wofull state of thys our realme of Englande set forth in a dialogue or communicacion betwene Eusebius and Theophilus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100967</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836794</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11528)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1187:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A trewe mirrour or glase wherin we maye beholde the wofull state of thys our realme of Englande set forth in a dialogue or communicacion betwene Eusebius and Theophilus.</title>
                  <author>Saunders, Laurence, d. 1555, attributed author.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by H. Singleton?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. Domi. M.D.L.VI. [1556]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed, doubtfully, to Laurence Saunders.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Bound with: R.V.  The olde fayth of greate Brittaygne, and the newe learnynge on Inglande (STC 24566).</note>
                  <note>Signatures C3v-C4r contain a metrical paraphrase of the Lord's Prayer.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A trewe <hi>mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROVR OR GLASE</hi> wherin we maye beholde the wofull ſtate of thys our Realme of Englande, ſet forth in a Dialogue or communicacion bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wene Euſebius and Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matthewe. 12.</bibl>
               <p>☞Omne regnum in ſe diuisum deſolabitur.</p>
            </q>
            <p>☞Imprinted. Anno. Domi. M.D.L.VI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:2"/>
            <head>A Dialogue <hi>OR COMMVNI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacion</hi> betwene Euſebius, and The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilus.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVſebius,</speaker>
               <p>what Theophilus God ſaue you, howe is your there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Euen better then I am worthy brother Euſebius. I thanke you for that you would inquier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>What man why ſaye you ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I am euill of my ſelfe and yet my Lord rewardeth me with good thynges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Lo nowe commeth to my remembraunce thynges that I haue been oftentymes deſirous to talke with you therein. But be ye nowe at leaſure, or whether bee ye going?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Surely into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feldes for to take the ayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer in better ſeaſon, I wyll goe wyth you euery fote: peraduenture ye maye put me from doutes, wherein my head hath ben often troubled, and of a long tyme I haue determyned to talke with you therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>What thynges are they ye meane?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>I wil tell you. Ye knowe well there hath been great dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion as wel among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> learned, as other, about Religion a greate whyle. The one Is called the olde mumſimus, the other the newe ſumpſimus the one a Catholike, the other a proteſtaunt, and the one a papiſt, the other an heretike, and ſuch lyke, which ought not to be me thynketh among Chriſtians ſpecially beyng of one nacyon and contree, who ſhould loue together as brethren,
<pb facs="tcp:1081:3"/>
now for that our frendſhyp hath been of longe continuaunce and youre honeſtye to me ſo well knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doutles brother Theo. I am ſorye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhoulde be noted to be of any euil opinion, and not ſuche as I mought w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out daunger frequent and vſe your company for aſſuredly there is no man otherwiſe that I deſyer more to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt withal then with you. And now the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ſuche, not onely towardes God, but alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperiours, Ring, Quene and maieſtrates that of force I am conſtrayned more oftener to leue youre company, then gladly I woulde, If I mought ſafly vſe the ſame. And thys is my grefe the which If I could I woulde ſurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue. And If I were able, I would perſwade you to conformyte wyth vs in religion In ſuch wyſe as we mought during our liues continew together our frendſhyp vnuiolated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Your lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing kindnes and frendſhip towardes me (bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Euſebius) I thankefullye embrace. And your approued honeſty moueth me to ſeake all meanes with you lykewyſe to continewe thys oure wonted frendſhippe and familiaritie. But there is a God hath created vs, vnto whom we owe a deuty, which muſt be done, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng all frendſhippe or obedience vnto man, and whereas you feare the daunger towardes God, for myne opinion. If it pleaſed God I would there were no more daunger otherwiſe, and then would not I dout the continuaunce of our frendſhip. For as touchyng myne opinion in religion, I am righte well aſſured that it is grounded vpon the infallible verite of goddes moſt ſacred worde or holy ſcriptures. From the
<pb facs="tcp:1081:3"/>
which If I ſhould ſtart backe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip or for feare of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it were as much as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord my god, which ye know no good man wil doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Yet but heare me Theophi. We doe not diſalow holy ſcriptures neyther doe we de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney the lorde but confeſſe both. But we doe ſift out errours, which light perſons haue brought in by miſvnderſtanding the holy Scriptures, and ſo bryng in againe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true light of the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>In dede ſo you ſay but how doe you proue it I would fayne here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Nay alas brother Theophilus ye knowe I am not ſo farre lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as to diſpute the matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>ſurely you are as wel able to make an argument as I am able to anſwere to the ſame. For I am no ſchole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but for the ſatiſfying of euery mans conſcyence and for diſcharge of myne owne, I alwayes ſeake vnderſtanding, leaſt by my to much ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenes or rather neglygence, I moughte be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, when I thinke my ſelfe moſt ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>In that I cannot diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend you, but then ye know they haue been diſputed withall at ful, ſo large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly as they coulde wiſhe or deſier, but nothynge can preuayle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I praye you where was that diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ye ſpeake of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Forſoth they were had in the conuocation houſe, howbeit for that they made their boaſt that thoſe men were but of the youngeſt ſorte, and yet they did ſo well there, how much better was it ſuppoſed the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent learned ſhould doe? Vpon thys report I ſuppoſe they prouided the diſputacions in ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde where the beaſt learned of your ſide were appoynted and diſputed: and yet god knoweth they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted and ouer come: for they wer
<pb facs="tcp:1081:4"/>
able In maner to make no repugnaunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you brother Euſe. were you there at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearing of thys diſputacions In Oxforde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>No verely that I was not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>but haue you ſene the copye of the ſame that was drawen out by theyr notaryes and geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenſours for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſyng of the trouth herein?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Neyther that haue I ſene In dede, but beeyng at ſupper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my frendes on a tyme I heard them talke of it In ſuche wyſe as I tolde you beefore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>But I praye you tell me one thyng, was not the relacion made by a preſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Yes doutles that it was, and it was in a prieſtes houſe, I maye ſay to you, a canon, one that may diſpend foure hundreth marke by the yere but what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? they ſayd it was trewe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>in dede if they ſayd ſo, yt muſt nedes be true, for they cannot lye, but yet this much I wil ſay vnto you brother Euſe. I was there preſente at the doing of thys geare, and heard al for the moſt part with mine eares: the which thing would god you and all honeſt men had heard and I dare ſay you would haue lamented the ſtate of thoſe .iii. men whych wer appointed to anſwere for theyr lyues, although otherwyſe ye miſlyke theyr Iudgemente in reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion. And yet I cannot tell what God ſhoulde haue wrought In you neyther by hearyng ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of: for like as I did knowe dyuers more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed in the fayth they had before receaued, ſo heard I of none that by the dyſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were with drawen from the ſame: alas good menne they coulde bee ſuffered to dooe no otherwyſe, but as the maſter wyll ſuffer hys ſeruaunt or ſcholar to ſpeake what he liſt to heare, &amp; while
<pb facs="tcp:1081:4"/>
he wyll heare hym and no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>What ſaye you man? It was a free diſputacion, and they ſpake and did what they would, as touchynge the order of diſputacion: this went the reporte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Wel what ſoeuer the reporte was I wyll tell you ſome parte of the order therof, wherein I wil not lie vnto you one word: Theſe doctours that came from london &amp; Cambrige, of whiche doctor Weſton was cheffe, for that he was pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loquutor of the conuocacion houſe, theſe men I ſay came to oxforde thys the frydaye, and the ſaterdaye folowyng were the .iii. pryſoners cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led forth before them and appointed to diſpute the monday, tueſdaye, and weddenſdaye folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, and beefore that I dare ſaye they knewe of no diſputacion, and aſſone as the diſputacion was appointed, Immediatly were they ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and coulde not conferre nor talke together: theyr owne bokes that they had laboured, and there commun places that they had gathered, was all taken from them when they came firſte to pryſon, and when they ſhoulde come foorthe to diſpute they were brought wyth bylles and glayues, as if they ſhould haue gone to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging: and there muſt one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone aunſwere ſome tymes .vi. ſpeaking to hym at one time, and euer would they crye vpon him to cutte ſhort, for the tyme was ſpent. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it came to maſter Rydleys torne, he had prouided hys ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thinkynge to haue reade it, but they woulde not ſuffer hym. And yet he alledged for himſelf the order of the ſcoles, and that al that litel time he had beſtowed in deuiſing the ſame, wherein he mynded to haue declared the ſubſtaunce of his aſſercion of hys fayth and beleue touching
<pb facs="tcp:1081:5"/>
that matter then in queſtion, but he coulde not be ſuffred in any wiſe, and ſondry tymes in hys talke they woulde take hym at aduauntage, and when he woulde open hys meaninge hys tale could not be heard of the audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but yet there were that noted hys woordes. Nowe I praye you what indifferency is thys? a man wythout ſtudy, wythout bokes, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference with other, and almoſt without hearing ſhal diſpute for hys lyfe? And they ſo many clappyng, at one tyme agaynſt one poore man, alas it was a grefe. And yet for all thys I warrant you they be not haſty in puttyng forth the diſputations in print, as much as they bragge I dare ſay they wyl neuer put them forth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>But is thys true that ye haue now ſayd in thys matter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Yea as trewe as god lyueth. And I dare ſaye If ye talke with the doctours themſelues that diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted agaynſt them they can deny none of al thys that I haue ſaid: wel they may couler it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome other thyng, but aſſuredly they cannot alter it, it is ſo openly knowen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Well brother Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men be in authorite, and haue the gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce In theyr hand, ſome what they will doe. And conſider alſo that in kynge Edwardes tyme your doctours dealte in lyke caſe with our learned men, And therfore blame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not though they now ſhow a litell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame curteſy againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Nay then marke what I wil ſaye vnto you brother Euſebius. And tell me whether the caſe bee lyke. In king Edwardes tyme there was appoynted a diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were .iii. of your learned againſt one of ours they had leyſure as muche as they woulde axe,
<pb facs="tcp:1081:5"/>
they were not taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr bokes, neither put in pryſon, they mought co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferre wyth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would, and go whether they would, they were not ſo much as checkte for defendyng their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Another tyme alſo I doe remember wel, that before Kyng Edward died, I was preſent at the diſputacion In oxford, where one Grene waye (a bacheler of diuinitie and the vice pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Corporis Chriſti Colledge) aunſwered and hys queſtion was, whether Chriſtes natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral body mought be in more places then one.</p>
               <p>there was one of the opponentes that openlye profeſſed hymſelfe to bee of a contrarie mynd, and ſo diſputed, and yet I neuer knewe ſo much as one euil woorde ſpoken to hym. Note nowe the tiranny that is vſed of the one ſyde whyche Chryſt neuer taught. And marke there great ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes agayne of the other ſyde. And this were inough almoſt to perſwade an honeſt heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Surely brother. Theophi. I woulde Charitie mought rule thys matter, for I doe verely bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that if wyth loue and frendeſhyp they dyd gentely commen together of theſe matters they ſhould much rather agree then by ſuche proude diſputations or rather ſcoldyng and brawling one with another. For to what purpoſe ſerueth thys cankored malice but the one to ſeke the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſtruction. And while we goe about miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheffe to eche other, there be that wyl deſtroye vs both: and then we haue ſpun a fayer threde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>In dede your gathering ſtandeth with good reaſon, and not without good authoryte of the holy Scriptures. For thys ſayeth the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus: Euery kyngdome within it ſelfe deuydede
<pb facs="tcp:1081:6"/>
ſhalbe deſtroied,<note place="margin">Math. 12 Luke. 11. Gala. 5.</note> and euery houſe deuided with in it ſelfe, ſhall not ſtande. And Saincte Paule ſayeth alſo if ye bite one another, take hede leſt ye be conſumed one of an other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>I praye you brother The. In what place is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt ſaith Euery kyngdome deuided wythin it ſelfe ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>In the .12. Chapter of Mathes goſpel and in the .11. of Luke likewiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurely I am affrayed leſt thoſe wordes are to trewe, and leſt we ſhal haue to much experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Wel brother Euſe. You nede not care, for you are a good Catholyke man, and therefore no harme can happen to you, for the game goeth on your ſyde. As for me ye know I am halfe ſuſpected and more. And therefore I loke when I ſhalbe called forth cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nobis and ſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyer, a cruell death I tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Wil ye beleue me brother Theophi. As god helpe me I am none of thoſe that deſireth the hurt of my neybour, and I tel you truth, I lyke thys religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the worſſe for there crueltie. For vndoutedly If the matter were in my hande there ſhoulde none be put to death except he would obſtinat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebell by commocions, or otherwyſe moleſte a whole commen wealth, as for hys conſcyence let hym diſcharge that betwene God and hym ſelfe, he ſhould choſe for me, for any trouble I would worke him, for me thinkes it ſtandes not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Charitie.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I miſtruſt you not brother Euſe. I know you to wel and like you the better. And in dede ſainct Paul ſayth: If I had fayth that, I could moue mountaynes out of there places, If I had not loue, I am nothyng. And Chryſte hym ſelfe ſaieth alſo:<note place="margin">Iohn. 14</note> by thys ſhal al men knowe
<pb facs="tcp:1081:6"/>
that ye are my diſciples, yf ye loue one another, the which loue ſpringeth from a faith vnfained in the promiſe of god, and cauſeth good workes to procede, as the frutes come of the buddinges of the tree.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>What bee thoſe good workes ye meane?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Mary callyng vpon the name of the lyuing god, by diligent, feruent, and continual prayer, in watchyng the deuill, that neyther by the luſt of thys fleſhe neyther yet by ambicion, and coueteouſnes, of thys wycked world, or by any other meanes, he ſhould ouercome vs, and ſubdue vs vnto ſynne. And therfore as we feel our ſelues prone, and apte to euil, ſo ſtil to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie theſe members of ours, by faſtynge, and prayer with ſuch like Godly exerciſes, to viſete and comforte our nedy neybours and ſo forth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you now, doe you ſpeake as you thinke, or els Ieſt ye with me to ſee what I wil ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I ſpeake it with my heart, as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as God lyueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Then haue I heard fouell lyes among them that would be accounted ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and wel learned. But ſeing we haue entred ſo farre in the matter I praye you certyfye me of the truth in this point, whether it be ſo or no: that I be not deceaued therin, for the ſatiſfying of my conſcyence and for quieting the ſame, for as for me although I be not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new learning, yet am I not ſo addicted to the olde, but that I would be glad to here and reaſon the matter, to thende I promyſe you I mought helpe to bring loue amonges our ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>A godly purpoſe I aſſure you, but what are thoſe lyes then ye heard of late, I praye you let vs heare them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Nay ſoft I ſayd not precyſely they were lyes,
<pb facs="tcp:1081:7"/>
but if that be trew, which you ſay, then are they lies in dede, but ſay on I pray you, what was that true tale then:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Syr thys it was tolde me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you of this new learnyng, dyd boaſt your ſelues much of fayth and that onely fayth dyd iuſtifie: but good workes ye cared not for, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regarded at all, neyther prayer nor faſtyng nor almes dede wil ye allow, goddes ſeruice ye deſpyſe and the miniſters therof with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande lyke, I cannot wel remember all nowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T</speaker>
               <p>I durſt lay a wager before hande that thys alſo was a Prieſtes tale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurelye it was ſo in dede, what a Goddes name howe are you ſo wel acquaynted with Prieſtes tales?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Yes I know them wel and theyr maſter alſo but bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Euſebius thys is no ſtraunge thynge, for there is no ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almoſt in theſe daies but theſe tales bee in the pulpet as thicke as hoppes and many lies more to: the which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I heare it ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth my hearte mourne to ſee their ſpyte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue no other way to worke their anger vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs but with ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lies in an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audience and yet the ſhame would redounde to themſelues, if there were any ſhame in them. For the moſte parte of men doe knowe moſt certenly that they doe lye. If they were of god as they pretende, or if they meant the preſeruacion of a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth and ſafegarde of their countrye, they woulde vſe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother waye of perſwaſion, they woulde haue charitie before theyr eyes, they would conſider the nature of euery man by themſelues and doe as they woulde bee done vnto: and I praye you who can ſuffer hymſelfe to be complained of to a whole countrye and to heare falſe wytneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:1081:7"/>
broughte agaynſte hym, and by thys meanes broughte to loue: no no, this is not to wynne theyr brethren, but euer to prouoke myſcheffe, and to ſet men by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares. God be merciful vnto vs the pulpet was ordained to ſpeake trueth, to preache peace, and to bryng vnitie among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren. And nowe they haue made it a place to ſprede lyes, to ſowe diſcorde, and to ſette mens hartes on fyer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enuy and malice. I am righte wel aſſured that if men would deny it, that the ſtones of the ſtrete would witnes that the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers in Kyng Edwardes tyme cried out vpon the ſinnes of men, and thretned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt extreme damnation, if they repented not and turned not to the Lord in ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of lyffe, and ſhewed them alſo a forehand what would come of oure wicked liuing, which thinges are come to paſſe, and therfore dyd continually exhort them to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentaunce with the niniuites, and to call vpon the name of the lyuing god in faſtyng and ſacke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cloth mourning and weping for the day of gods wrath was at hand, as we haue right wel felte and are like to feale more yet. This was not one mans preaching alone, but al for the moſt part, and thys (I ſay) If men wil deny the ſtones of the ſtrete wil witnes the ſame. And yet al thys not wythſtandyng come they into the pulpets and ſaye: theſe newe felowes woulde haue no good workes, neyther faſtyng, nor prayer, but al libertie, libertie, faith, fayth, and nothing els Oh God what Chriſten hearte dooeth not euen breake with ſorow, to ſe ſuch ſlaunderers main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained in a pulpet: But god is a righteous lord and for that we would not be warned in tyme,
<pb facs="tcp:1081:8"/>
being ſo much called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he hath iuſtly placed vs, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pacience therfore we muſt beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe til it pleaſe him to take it of agayne, there is no remedy, for if we once ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our mouthes to reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the matter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this caſe, we muſt ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crow is whyte or els we goe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out redempci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, thys is a miſerable caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Ye make me aſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyed Theophilus. For howe may it be that they ſhould vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter ſo cruellye, if there were not ſome great cauſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I wil tell you Euſebius, I haue heard the preachers in Kyng Edwardes time a mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And haue red their workes, and if euer I found one ſentence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did diſcourage ani ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; not rather ſpurre forth euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doing of thoſe good workes aboue reherſed, let god forſake me, &amp; ſhow me no more his fauour &amp; grace. For although we do attrybute our iuſtificacion to onely fayth, and that by faith only we be iuſtified, we meane not a dead faith, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute workes, but a liuing fayth, euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame fayth ſainct Paul ſpeaketh of to the Galathians,<note place="margin">Gala. 5.</note> which by loue is mightie in opera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree therefore is knowen to be liuing by hys budding &amp; bearing of frute: ſo is the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiyng fayth knowen by charitie, out of which charitie, ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth theſe good workes aboue ſaid which are the very frutes therof. But your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke fathers ſhowe but litell or no charitye, and therfore it ſhould ſeme they haue but lytell or no fayth. Euſebius your reaſon is ſomewhat pithye, but yet I ſuppoſe there is ſomewhat els that moueth thys great contrauerſy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>In dede it is trewe, there is another thyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moueth the matter, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil the authour &amp; maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of contencion and miſchefe, in ſubmittyng
<pb facs="tcp:1081:8"/>
our ſelues where vnto we loſe innocency, loue, mekenes, &amp; al other vertues, and in ſtede therof we fynd pryde, ſtoutenes, hatred and ſuch like, as for coueteouſnes it ouer floweth the whole world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>But wil ye geue me leue (bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Theophilus) to ſay one thyng vnto you, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I know you to be ſuch a man, for youre honeſty, as I would deſier to leade my life w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al for your faithful &amp; trew heart is knowen to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue to doe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which thing chefe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly I haue reſpect vnto, and I doe beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath engrafted his grace in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mans hart, which dealeth iuſtly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men, &amp; liueth quietly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his familiars, ſpecially when it is wel knowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wiſheth al thinges to be wel. But yet (ye ſhal not be offended w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wil ſay) there were of your ſort, which are called the newe learnynge, many euil me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>It was moſt trew brother Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius and can not be denyed. For there were in hel no veryer deuils the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were that profeſſed the goſpel, for otherwyſe there could haue ben no couler of theſe lyes, and ſlaunders that are now ſpred, as is ſaid before. For it was Iudas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pouche, &amp; it was Iudas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> betrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed hys maſter: and many Iudaſſes in England vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pretence of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> robbed both Kynge and realme theſe iudaſſes filled their own pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, &amp; made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues riche &amp; noble, &amp; they care not who rule ſo long as they may geat &amp; enioye their poſſeſſions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Well brother Theophilus here are no more but you &amp; I, &amp; I dare be bolde herein to tel you my mind. For I know you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in it as muche as I, &amp; more to, &amp; I dare ſay you do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as great a gref behold it &amp; ſorow it
<pb facs="tcp:1081:9"/>
as any Engliſh heart wil doe. I heare ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of Spayne ſhal at laſt be crouned kyng of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what ſay you to that:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T</speaker>
               <p>Alas brother Euſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bius what ſhould I ſay to it: If god haue deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myned, who maye wythſtande: we muſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt it to his good pleaſure and wyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>But do you not thynke it a plage?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Yes verely and an vtter deſolacion of Engliſhe bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Oh lord what meaneth thys?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I wyll tell you brother Euſe. The almightie god hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning wrytten his wil and law, not in tables of ſtone onely, neyther in bokes of paper and ynke, but alſo in the heartes of men, as it is wrytten: I wryte my lawes in theyr heartes, and I wyl be theyr god and they ſhalbe my people. But leſte any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould dreame of theſe lawes and faine other in theyr ſtede they were written in tabels of ſtone, and after in bokes of paper and inke, ſo that to this day they are deuided and knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from mens lawes. And for our better inſtrucci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on herein the onely begotten ſonne of God oure Lord Ieſus Chryſt hath accordyng to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers promyſe ſtablyſhed and confyrmed a new teſtament, wherin he hath opened playnely the myſteries of Moyſes law and the Prophetes, not to breake them, as the falſe Phariſeis falſly reported of hym, but to fulfyl them in executing thys hys new teſtament. The which ſound doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of health, the world alwayes ſpurned at, as they doe yet to thys daye. And althoughe it were for a tyme ſuffered here in Englande by the prouidence of god, and moſt earneſtly prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched and publiſhed, yet was there that ſpurned at it, and many abuſed it for there libertie for co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetous
<pb facs="tcp:1081:9"/>
lucre and ſuch lyke, many warninges we had for both partyes to amende, but it woulde not be, wherfore ſeeing we woulde not receaue hym but deſpiſe hym ſtil as the Iewes dyd, we ſhal likewyſe be deſtroyed as they were I ſe no other remedy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>God be merciful vnto vs, but yet I meruayle that our nobilitie ſuffereth it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T</speaker>
               <p>Why man ye muſt vnderſtande that your catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lykes nowe beare the rule, youre prelates of the Churche haue al the doynges of theſe matters, and ye knowe they hauinge none inheritaunce but for their liues, beyng without wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, rather then they would be brought down agayne, as they were in king Edwardes dayes they had rather the Turke had the rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement therof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>I maye ſaye to you Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus they are ſhroudly ſuſpected in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and I feare me not without good cauſe. But yet I meruayle of the councellours, who being put in truſt with the gouernment and maye let the proceding hereof, what ſhoulde moue them to conſente thereunto:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>As I may thynke my ſelfe aſſured of you as you of me, and maye as boldely ſpeake alſo my mynde to you, as you to me, and although faythful frendeſhip be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baniſhed thys Realme, ſo that one brother al moſt cannot truſt another, yet frendſhip lurketh in corners ſecretely. And I thynke my ſelfe ſafe with you brother Euſebius. Your faythfulnes is to me ſo wel knowe. I wil therfore ſhow you what I coniecture to be the cauſe of their agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a lamentable caſe it is, and wyth great ſo row and grefe, muſt I tel you herein my mind. They be men that be louers of themſelues, yet
<pb facs="tcp:1081:10"/>
they are ſo blinded with this ſelf loue, that they neither can foreſee the miſerable ſtate of theyr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, neither yet their owne deſtruccion, they dreame as Pope Iulius dyd, who (as the fabel telleth) commaunded Sainct Peter to open hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen gates, dreamyng himſelfe to be Pope ſtyll. Theſe men dreame that the King of Spaine wil make them alwaye of hys chefe counſel but. &amp;c. They haue been of King Harry the eightes cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel, broughte vp of meane men the moſte parte. Wherby they ſhould be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted noble, I know not. For they excell not in learning and knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, they haue ſhowed no greate proues of armes, theyr loue to a common wealth is nowe declared. But they be ſo infected with ambicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that loke what pleaſeth the affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince pleaſeth alſo them. For in King Henryes daies they were ſworne to aboliſhe the popes ſupre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macy with his vſurped power, yea and they pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted the matter earneſtly as it appered right wel, for many loſt theyr liues for the ſame. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Kyng Henry was deade, Kyng Edwarde hys ſonne by the meanes of hys vncle then Lorde protectour ſubuerted al the Popes religion, put down maſſe and altogether, wherewithall they were well contented, and ſet forewarde the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter withoute any ſcruple of conſcyence, I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante you. And many goodly lawes they lette make, as wel for the mayntenaunce of that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as alſo for the preſeruacion of a commen wealth, and before Kyng Edwarde was fullye dead, they had concluded alſo with the Duke of Northumberlande, vnder pretence of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of that religion, and other goodly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideracions
<pb facs="tcp:1081:10"/>
as it were to make hym Kyng, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to al right, and contrary to all the ſtatutes of parlemente and ſo woulde haue diſheryted the Quene that nowe is, agaynſte her fathers wil, agaynſt theyr own lawes, agaynſt all their othes and promiſe, and without any iuſt cauſe, at that time. And al this notwithſtanding, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſawe how the game would goe: they were contented to ſerue the Quenes wyll, and nowe haue they ſworne backe agayne to the holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I heare ſay: now agayne wheras y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quene goeth about not onely to breake her fathers wil and al ſuch lawes &amp; ſtatutes as were made for the preſeruacion and ſafegarde of thys realme, but is alſo determined of a ſelfe wyll to brynge England into the ſubieccion of a foren Prynce, they haue not onely conſented and agreed, but are alſo chefe doers and procurers thereof, for god hath blynded theyr eyes, and theyr vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſo that they cannot ſee nor perceaue, their own deſtruccion, and yet euery child ſeeth and euery good heart mourneth at it ful heuely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurely Theophilus you haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as trewe as the goſpell, for if he be once ſtabliſhed King, he may without contradiccion furniſhe al the fortes in Englande with his owne men, for I would not thinke him wiſe to truſt ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers ſo muche as his own countre men: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath therefore brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to paſſe he may at all times bring an army either out of flaunders or ſpain, the ſhyppes being alſo at hys commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and thorow Englande may he goe at hys wyll and pleaſure, who wil ſay hym naye: Alas mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Nay nay Euſebius he ſhal nede
<pb facs="tcp:1081:11"/>
none army to bryng this matter to paſſe, for if the Quene liue ſeuen yeres to an ende, he wyll ſo vſe the matter that Englande ſhalbe eaſy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough to rule, for marke ye now how faſt the gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle men go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tower, yea and ſome to hanging alſo. And ye ſee the gentlemen for the moſt part be of this newe learnyng, and therfore ye know vnder pretence of religion there wilbe matters Inough to ridde the moſt part of the nobilite of Englande, and all thys ſhal we be made to doe within our ſelues, we ſhalbe inueigled thus to doe one agaynſt another by traynes and baites to ſeake one anothers deſtruccion, wherunto ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny are very preſt, and al to do the Quene a plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure. Marke how thys geare commeth to paſſe, for the Spaniard hath nothing to doe in al this (as we ſuppoſe) but rather getteth pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſhoweth great fauour to Englyſhe men, but ye may be ſure they haue debated thys matter in theyr heades, &amp; in all this they make the Quene ſerue their turne, and her own fancy alſo. Now when al theſe heretike gentlemen be diſpatched (which wylbe the greateſt part of the nobilitie of Englande) then ſhal there be other inuency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had for the reſt, which ſhalbe eaſy inough, for they ſhalbe fewe. And thynke you he wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſt Engliſhe men for the gouernment of hys kyngedome when he hath ſo weakened it, and may take the matter in hande? No for then per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aduenture the poore Engliſhe men maye take a ioye in their heades when they once begyn to feale the ſmarte, and an Englyſhe Lorde wilbe deinte at that tyme, and they wyll begynne to loue eche other, when they ſee howe the game
<pb facs="tcp:1081:11"/>
wil goe, and ſo ſhewe themſelues in their olde lykenes, and ſo make a foule worke. But I war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant you theſe men whiche can ſo compaſſe the matter to bryng it ſo farre forth, wil not be ouer ſene in thys, of that ye may be ſure. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of goe their heades alſo, let them poynt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it, and thus farewel the glory of Englande for euer and a day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>O Lord whether there be no remedy for Englande that it mought be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from thys miſerye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Surelye there is but one and that is a generall repentaunce with the Niniuites faſtyng and praying, moſte eare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtly calling vpon the trew liuing god to haue mercy vpon vs, for his ſonne Chriſtes ſake, and ſo leaue enuieng and hating ech other, and ſeake loue together as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth brethren: this way and none other can I ſee to eſcape.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Well god be mercifull vnto vs what ſhoulde I ſay, I can not tell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Your holy Prelates Euſebius haue preached a great whyle agaynſte our pore mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and haue layde to their charge that they haue ben great hinderers of a common wealth, and haue marred altogether by there doctrine, in pullyng down Abbeys and Colledges, wyth ſuch like, wherin although they ſpake agaynſte their ſuperſticion, and idle lyfe yet was it not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreſſed by their aduiſe, &amp; therefore dyd they con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually preache agaynſte the coueteouſ hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling therof, and the euil beſtowyng of ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, ye they feared not to tell them to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of there faultes, ſo openly and playnelye, as all Englande can ryghte well witnes the ſame. And yet for all that doe not your Prelates ceaſe to caſt them in the teth, as though they mought
<pb facs="tcp:1081:12"/>
haue ruled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roſt, beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruites of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne ſay they, for al was coueteouſnes, &amp; I can not tel what, but if ye note well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruite of their doctrine, ye ſhal perceaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue brought a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother maner of thyng to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of vs al, the whych thing vndoutedly muſt nedes come to paſſe, if god doe not wonderfully worke for our preſeruacion, contrary to al mens expectacion, &amp; contrary alſo to our deſeruing, &amp; that ſhortly, for it is at hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Welcome by the grace of god. For euery kingdome deuided w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in it ſelfe ſhalbe deſtroyed I haue learned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and I ſhall not forget it as longe as I lyue: but yet I am not fully ſatiſfied of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matter wherof I ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded moſt to reaſon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you, but now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing draweth on, &amp; peraduenture I let you from your buſines.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>In dede myne houre is almoſt come wherein I promyſed to mete a frende of myne. But if it pleaſe you to pointe any time to morowe I wil mete you here by Goddes grace. And we wyl haue the matter debated at full.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Syr I praye you hartely let it be to morow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dyner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Wyth a good wil, fare ye wel</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>and I pray god geue you his holy ſpirite to order &amp; rule your goinges, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ye go about, it maye be to the honour &amp; glory of his name, &amp; to the profit of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>with all my hearte, &amp; I pray god it may ſo come to paſſe. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:12"/>
            <head>¶The ſeconde <hi>DIALOGVE OR</hi> communicacion betwene Euſebius and Theophilus.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVſebius,</speaker>
               <p>well mette brother Theophilus, you haue made good ſhifte, I thought to haue been heare before you, you wente to diner betyme I perceaue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Euen as I doe commonly, when I haue no buſynes, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wene nyne &amp; ten, me thinkes it is a good houre: for by that meanes I ſaue a breakefaſt, whyche for ſuche idlers as I am, is moſte fitteſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>In dede to ſay truth it were inough, for the moſte part of men, if they could be ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Yea brother Euſebius, and a greate deale of thoſe two meales in one daye, would be better ſpente alſo. I meane of ſuch, as vſe muche banketynge and coſtly fare dayly in theyr houſes, with ſuch ſuperfluyte, as ſurely is in mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to much, and none vſe it more, then your Prelates of the Churche: for they ſuppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to faſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, if they abſtayne from fleſhe frydayes and ſaterdayes, and ſuche lyke dayes as they haue appoynted: they thynke it no matter to ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket other dayes, and ſo are all the reſt of youre religion perſwaded. And yet alas conſyderyng the miſerable ſtate we ſtande in it were mere to mourne, wepe, faſt, and pray: I meane not fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes onely but all the dayes of the weake, to
<pb facs="tcp:1081:13"/>
leaue our bely chere and to take an other waye, then to banket and play, ſetting cocke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houpe and care not what beecome of vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue ſayed well Theophilus I promyſe you, but yet geue me leaue to ſaye agayne your ſort of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde deſpyſed ſo muche our ſuperſtycyous faſt, that they faſted not at all, and therfore our men were the better in thys caſe I am ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt nedes graunt Euſebius that a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were at that poynte, and I muſt confeſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that libertye had cauſed many men to waxe wylde, the whiche woulde haue been tamed, by good lawes right well, and were in maner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided. If Satan had not enuied the profit ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But yet they ſay there can be neuer a better, wheras there is neuer a good, but as touchyng dyet, doutleſſe I thynke there were ſome good men of both ſides, I meane ſuche men as wyth good moderacion vſed gods creatures for there neceſſitie, and not for theyr wanton luſt. And ſo likewiſe in other outward obſeruaunces, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there be of both ſides, that meane wel, and wyſhe well vnto all men, and I doe not thynke the contrarye but if there were charitie in oure heartes, &amp; we could fynd in our heartes to loue one another, we ſhould agree and proſper well inough, but Sathan hath ſowed the ſeade of diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde among vs, and we cannot loue eche other, but wyth moſte ſpite that may be, we perſecute one another to deſtruccion, and thys wylbe our own confuſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Yea Theophilus that is in dede a lamentable thyng and the greateſt grefe to me, that you beyng an honeſt man, and I am I hope not of the worſt ſort of men, for my har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye
<pb facs="tcp:1081:13"/>
deſier is that all moughte be well, thys ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore greueth me that we ſhould be of diuers opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nions, and not of one mynd ſpecially in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and therefore dyd I couet to talke wyth you to thende I moughte if I coulde bryng you to the ſame mynd I am my ſelfe, and to ſay the trueth I vnderſtande not ſo great contrauerſye, but as you ſayd with charite and frendly debating the matter we ſhal agree, and ſo would I wyſhe all men to doe, for I lyke not thys crueltye aſſured<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and therfore let me underſtande wherein we vary, we beleue both al the Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten fayth, what cauſeth the contrauerſye there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I wyll tell you Euſebius, the name of the catholyke churche, the holy churche, the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall churche, that marreth altogether.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſe.</speaker>
               <p>What man ſay not ſo, god forbydde, but Chryſt ſhoulde haue a churche heare in earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>loe ſyr howe ſone ye miſunderſtande me. I remember now, that when maſter Latymer beganne fyrſt to preache, he taughte the people to putte theyr hole confydence in Ieſus Chryſt, and that he on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly was our redempcion and that there was no health in any other, no not in the bleſſed virgyn Mary (ſayeth he) I wil not ſay but ſhe was the moſt excellent woman vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, and ſauoured altogether of Chryſt, as the bagge wherein ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron hath been ſmelleth altogether of ſaffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet is not the bagge the ſaffron it ſelfe, and ſo was not ſhe the ſaueoure ſelfe, thoughe ſhe bare hym that was ſaueour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to as many as bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued in hym, thys wyth more Eloquent wordes did he ſet forth, as he was a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſing al other for that purpoſe, now what ſayd the people of
<pb facs="tcp:1081:14"/>
thys? Forſouth that he had deſpyſed our lady, and had made her no better then a ſaffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bagge I bryng thys tale by the way nowe, not ſo much for that you miſtoke me in thys, as to put you in remembraunce of the great foly that is in many now a daies, whiche when they heare, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture vnderſtande not the matter, yet wyll they goe and tell a whole ſtorye, and euer they wyll make the wurſte of it, thys it is almoſte in euery commen matter betwene neyghboure and neyghbour: there be ſuch a ſort of peace brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that delite in nothing ſo much as in telling of newes and thus ſetteth one neyghboure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt another, all whiche encreaſeth oure da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>But dyd I then miſunderſtande you Theophilus: Theo Yea brother Euſebius, but thankes be to god there can be no hurt in that. I ſpeake all thys, for no other thyng but that you ſhould note the great miſcheffe that inſueth of thoſe flatterers whyche gooe flerynge to picke thanke, and tell all they heare and more to, and that to woorke miſchefe, but this is no ſuche matter: for althoughe you toke me that I ſayed that Chryſtes churche or the holy catholyke churche marred altogether yet ſhall we debate the matter before we goe, ſo that we ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande one another, but theſe men ſeake no ſuche thing that I ſpake of before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>But then I pray you, let me vnderſtande your meaning, for ſo I toke it in dede as for ſuche peace breakers as ye ſpake of, I knowe and coulde declare howe by: ſuche of a ſparcle was made a whole fyer, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough to haue ſet a whole contree on a heate, but let that paſſe and goe forth I pray you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Thus
<pb facs="tcp:1081:14"/>
I ſayed Euſebius, that the name of the holye catholyke churche, the vniuerſall churche, or of Chryſtes churche, if ye wyll, that dooeth marre altogether.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo? Theophilus, for thys cauſe, that they whyche pretende to bee Chriſtes church, are nothing leſſe then Chriſtes in dede. Euſebius doe ye thinke ſo? Theophilus yea and I wil proue it ſo to, that you ſhal vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande that your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>ſay on I pray you, and I wil geue eare. Theophilus this know ye firſt then, that in the .24. Chapter of Saincte Mathewes goſpell, Chryſt gaue hys diſciples thys warnyng and ſayed: take hede, for many ſhal come in my name &amp; ſaye there are Chriſtes, be not deceaued. &amp;c. Nowe ye muſte vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that Chriſtus is as much to ſay as annointed, ſo that many ſhall come in Chryſtes name and ſay they be the annoynted, marke wel this warning and take good hede vnto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Well forth yet, I doe vnderſtande you wel thys farre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Verye well then note thys alſo, that as the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus gaue thys warning a litel before hys death, ſo dyd Saincte Paull alſo a greate whyle after Chryſt had ſuffred, cal the Biſhops and elders of Epheſus together, and taking hys leaue, as one that ſhould ſee them no more, gaue them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thys warning and ſayed, take hede vnto your ſelues, and to the flocke wherof ye haue charge: for after my departyng ſhall enter in among you greuous wolues,<note place="margin">Acte. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> which ſhal not ſpare the flocke &amp;c. Marke well now that Chriſte the Lord, and hys Apoſtles lykewyſe, howe diligently and er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtly they gaue vs warninge to take hede and beware of deceauers, and falſe Prophetes, yea
<pb facs="tcp:1081:15"/>
as it were almoſte theyr laſte woordes, whyche of all other, for the moſte parte, are to be noted. and were it not reaſon we dyd take hede?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſe.</speaker>
               <p>Yes doutleſſe, we muſte and ought to take hede or els we ſhalbe deceaued. But nowe ſaye oure Preachers that we oughte to take hede of you, for of you were theſe woordes ſpoken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Naye then marke Sainct Paules wordes agayne, for he ſayeth: after my departing. &amp;c. And they ſhal be men that ſhall ryſe euen of your own ſelues, ſayeth he.<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.</note> And Saincte Iohn in hys Epiſtles ſayeth alſo that euen then in hys tyme were ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny become Antichriſtes alredye. And therefore the daunger is not nowe onely, but then and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be taken hede vnto. And it is the more daunger in that they ſhall come in the name of Chryſt, pretendyng hys authoritye, and by that meanes the rather deceaue the good ſimple ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beholde therefore I haue told you before, ſaith the Lorde take hede. &amp;c. Euſebius well yet I ſe not in al this, but we haue as good cauſe to take hede of you as you of vs and more to, for we are of greatter authorite, and better can we ſhowe for our ſelues then you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>That woulde I faine vnderſtand for therein lyeth the whole matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Wel ſir then harken, firſt we are come to this poynt that betwene vs is ſtryfe, whether we ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholikes be the true churche of Chryſt, and you proteſtauntes falſe Prophetes, or els we the falſe harlottes, and you the trewe men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſaye trueth, nowe for the profe of your authory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye, and that your catholykes be the true church of Chryſte, let vs heare what you can ſaye,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
               <p>Thus I ſaye then, that our churche hath been of
<pb facs="tcp:1081:15"/>
a long continuaunce, from Chryſtes tyme vnto thys daye, and it hath been alſo vniuerſall tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe out all Chryſtendome, not here or there but thorowe oute. And they haue alwayes one conſente within them ſelues, now by theſe thre poyntes doe the greateſte learned men geue a ſure and certayne knowledge of the true church vnto all men, that is to wite by antiquite, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſalite, and conſent, and me thynkes it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent, for it cannot deceaue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you thynke thys a ſufficient proffe:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Yea douteleſſe, what can you ſaye to the contrarye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Mary I ſay that by this reaſon ye maye proue the Scrybes and Pharyſes to bee the true churche, and Chryſte to be a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, for they profeſſed Moiſes law and obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued it alſo better then your Catholikes doe now the goſpel, and thys law ye know was of great antiquitie, and ſo were alſo many of theyr own tradicions, that they had deuyſed beſyde that lawe, ſo that they had antiquite ſufficiente, and vniuerſall they were thoroweout all Iuda and Ieruſalem, as we thorowe Chryſtendome: and theyr conſentye may vnderſtande by the death of Chryſte, whereunto they all conſented and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but ye muſt vnderſtande that oure churche begane fyrſte at Chryſte, and ſo from thence had her antiquitie, and from him it beganne to be vniuerſall, and in hym the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente is effectuall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Naye then ye make your matter wurſie then before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius</speaker>
               <p>Dooe I ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verely doe ye, for tell me, what thynke you of the churche of the Apoſtles, was not that a perfecte true churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1081:16"/>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Yes verely, and ſo perfect, as I bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue there hath not been a perfecter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus</speaker>
               <p>Very well, but I praye you, of what antiquitie were theyr You graunt that Chryſt was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynner of that churche beyng here a liuing man on earth. And then howe could they alledge for themſelues antiquitie. And ſeyng they had not your markes, ſpecially antiquitie, it ſhoulde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by your reaſon not to be the true churche, or els if ye graunte that to bee the true churche, and your churche and that churche haue not like probacion, then muſte youre churche be a falſe churche there is no remedy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Ye play the ſophiſter with me now brother Theophilus</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Naye truly the reaſon is ſo playne that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ploweman maye well vnderſtande the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>Well yet if they hadde not that antiquitie, which we haue, this maketh no diſcorde among vs, for we haue antiquitie by the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue continued ſo longe in that doctryne, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, whiche they deliuered vnto vs, &amp; now therfore is that ſame waxen olde by time, which then was new begon: and therfore thys is but a cauillacion of ſophiſters to ſhyft of an inconue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niaunce, whyche els would enſewe: and thys is the maner of ſubtyle diſputers, as the moſt part of your opinion be ſubtile diſputers, and haue good heades full of inuencion, and douteleſſe many of them haue much learninge, I moughte ſaye to muche well inoughe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>That is the common ſaying of your catholykes nowe, and yet I remember within theſe fewe yeares, when they woulde crye oute and ſaie: they haue no learning at all, but onely haue redde an Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhe
<pb facs="tcp:1081:16"/>
booke, a to peny boke, as for learning they had none. And nowe agayne they ſaye, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue all the worlde by to muche learnyng, thys they ſaye, they care not what, ſo they be talking. But nowe whereas you thynke myne obieccion to be but a cauillacion, ye muſte vnderſtande that it is a greate matter to deceaue men in the pryncypall poynte of our fayth, as to reache vs to knowe the churche by a falſe meane, as they ſaye by antiquitie, whereas ye knowe the beſte churche had it not. But then whereas ye vrge antiquitie nowe, for that ye haue of longe tyme continued in the doctryne and obſeruaunces of the Apoſtles I denye that, and put you to your proues, wherin doe ye continew in the Apoſtles doctryne and obſeruaunces.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Forſeth in all thynges that the churche teacheth, there is nothyng as I thynke, but the Scripture dooeth teache the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Then I praye you tell me in what place of the Scripture doe you fynde, that we ought to knele downe, to crepe, and kyſſe Images, to ſence them, to decke them, and trime them wyth ſuch lyke, or els rather tel me in how many places of the Scripture we be commaunded to the contrarye. As in the ſecond commaundemente and a thouſande places bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide: and like as in that poynte, ſo almoſt in all the reſte I could proue that your catholykes do not onely not folowe the doctrine of the holye Scripture but alſo teache another doctryne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to the ſame: now if they wyll yet for all that boaſt themſelues of Chryſte, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and yet teache another doctryne contrary to the holy Scriptures: oughte we not to take
<pb facs="tcp:1081:17"/>
hede and beware of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Well yet tell me thys one thynge, hath not Chryſte had a Churche heare in earth euer ſence hys reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, hath not the churche preached and continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed viſible, a knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churche ſtyl in al places, not in corners heare or there but thorowe oute all Chriſtendom, &amp; openly had the rule, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the whole congregacion from time to time? And your churche beganne of late yeares, was a ſtraunge thyng not knowen, but a litell whyle in a fewe places of Germanye and ſo heare in England, but it is quailed againe wythin ſhort ſpace: and yet I cannot tell howe, if it had been the trewe churche of Chryſt, it could not ſo ſone haue been ouerthrowen, wherfore if there were nothyng els but this reaſon, yet is it ſufficiente to ſtablyſh the conſciences of good ſimple men. For there can be nothyng ſayd vnto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>Yes Euſebius if ye liſt to hearken I wyll aunſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>were you in ſuche wyſe as I truſt you ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E.</speaker>
               <p>I wyl hearken gladlye Theophilus, for if ye can anſwere me to this, I haue no more to ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Then heare me I pray you, I graunt you that Chryſt hath had a churche or congregacion heare in yearth, whyche hath con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually preached hys goſpell, hys teſtamente, hys holy worde from his reſurreccion yea from the begynnyng vnto thys daye, theſe have been viſible, and knowen, as Iohn the Baptyſt was knowen to Herode, Chryſte was knowen to the Iewes, for Iohn was behedded, and Chryſte was crucified, and whiche of the Apoſtles eſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped that was not putte to death, ſome hanged, ſome broiled, ſome roſted, ſome one cruel death
<pb facs="tcp:1081:17"/>
and ſome another, and therefore ye may be ſure they were knowen. And yet becauſe ye ſhall not ſaye but euen the Apoſtles hydde them ſelues and fledde, ye reade howe Saincte Paule was lette down in a baſket ouer the wall and wente hys waye, and I praye you howe many yeares after the Apoſtles were the menne of God vexed and perſecuted? And all this was for preaching the goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt. Nowe whereas ye laye to oure charge that our churche beganne but of late, your churche is the more to be ſuſpected for that, which haue ſo longe ſpace kepte downe the goſpell, for we profeſſe none other doctrine then the Apoſtles and Martyrs did, whiche died for it, as ye ſee howe our prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and diuers other good brethren are conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to geue ouer theyr lyues lykewyſe for the ſame, as the Apoſtles dyd. For Chryſte hath taughte in dyuers places that we ſhould ſuffer for his doctrine, but he neuer taught to kyll any for it. The rule that your Prelates haue taken ouer the churches, hath been and yet is like prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and not lyke Apoſtles: they playe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers, but not the ſaueours: they folow their maſter the deuill, and not oure maſter Chryſte. And therefore lette no man thynke that Chryſte mayntayneth hys churche in ſuche pompe and pryde, but rather layeth on them the croſſe, for he ſayeth the ſeruaunte is not greater then hys Lorde: yf they haue perſecuted me they ſhall alſo perſecute you and ſo foorth. But nowe youre Prelates fynde oute ſuche balde reaſons to perſwade the ſymple to be of theyr ſide, and ſay they, where are theſe new felowes become?
<pb facs="tcp:1081:18"/>
they be gone, but Chriſtes churche is a viſible churche a knowen churche, &amp; not hydde in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But ſheweth her ſelfe openlye. And ſuche like. But I praye you where was theyr churche in Kinge Edwardes dayes: If there were no more reaſons to proue it a falſe church but that ſame one, it were ſufficiente to proue them falſe diſſemblers. For where as Chriſtes Apoſtles, diſciples, and many Martyrs after that would rather loſe theyr lyues then denye theyr maſter or his doctryne: they were contented not onely to ſubſcribe, but alſo to preach earneſtly againſt that whiche they nowe defende: if ye will haue one named, axe the Byſhoppe of London whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he haue not preached agaynſte the Pope? Yea and whyche of them hath not? where was there any of them that woulde burne hys lytell fynger for the maintenaunce of theyr doctryne? And nowe ye ſee the other companye, hauinge another maner of hope of the reſurreccyon, they come and offer themſelues. I tel you trueth heare is a great difference, and if, yet for al this, you wyll haue that Chryſtes churche, which is ſo addycted to the worlde, that for ſafegard of their liues and liuinges, they wil ſay whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſhal: then Chriſtes churche were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully chaunged from that it was in the bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge. Weye you the matter in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence brother Euſebius. Yea behold what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they haue in ſhedding of bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ye haue layde ſoore to my charge bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Theophilus, and to ſaye the trueth, theyr tyrannye my ſtomake dooeth abhorre But yet tell me one thynge, if theſe ſignes, and tokens
<pb facs="tcp:1081:18"/>
be vncerten to knowe Chryſtes churche, howe doe you know the trewe ſpouſe of Chriſt? what tokens canne you ſhowe me whereby I mighte aſſuredly knowe Chryſtes churche and not bee deceaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>I will tell you brother Euſebius, but firſte call to remembraunce, the warninge that Chryſte gaue vs to be ware of falſe Prophetes, and alſo the admonycyon of Sayncte Paull to the ſame ende, and the wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Sayncte Iohn, who affyrmed that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were come in his tyme, and in many places of Sayncte Paull, ye ſhall ſee howe he complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of them that they wente aboute to ſubuert the ghoſpell of Chryſte and that in the name of Chriſte. And therefore to thentente we ſhoulde not bee deceaued vnder the couler of holy aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente fathers or any ſuch lyke:<note place="margin">Gala. 1.</note> he gaue vs thys moſte certeyne and infallyble rule ſayinge: If we oure ſelues (marke well hys wordes) if we oure ſelues, or an Aungell from heauen preache vnto you a goſpell that hath not been preached already to you, holde hym accurſed. As I ſayd, ſo I ſaye agayne (ſayeth he) if we or an Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heauen preache vnto you another doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne whiche hath not been by vs preached al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, lette hym bee accurſed, and ſo foorth. Now tell me Euſebius, If youre catholyke churche doe preache any doctryne, beſyde or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarye to the doctryne of Saynct Paul and the reſte of the Apoſtles, haue we not here a playn rule to refuſe them and holde them accurſed? And haue we not here ſufficiente inſtruccion howe to knowe the perfect true churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius.</speaker>
               <p>Verely I cannot tell what to ſaye, for ye
<pb facs="tcp:1081:19"/>
haue almoſte caughte me in youre nette, but yet I will learne more argumentes to oppoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte you, the whiche if you canne lykewyſe ſolute, I wyll geue place, for me thynkes ye meane well, and I partlye doute whether in ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye dede ye haue the veritie on youre ſyde, the whyche being certenlye knowen, I will not bee aſhamed to confeſſe mine ignoraunce. For what ſhoulde we ſeake but the glory of Chryſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ophilus.</speaker>
               <p>Woulde God all Englyſhe men were lyke minded, I meane not that they ſhoulde ſtrayghte waye geue place to vs, but that they would quietlye bee contented to debate the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter charitably, brotherly and frendly: ſome there bee that woulde but they beare not the ſweye, and therefore with pacience we muſt remaine and beholde what the good wil and pleaſure of oure Lorde God is vpon vs, for our offences and ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurely the ſentence is geuen in euery kingedome within it ſelfe deui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded ſhal bee deſtroyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophi.</speaker>
               <p>Well the good wil of god be don. Except we may deceaue his Prophetes by earneſt repentaunce with the Ni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niuites as is ſayd before, as Ionas was decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, els there is no remedy. But yet who ſo put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his truſt in the lord ſhal not be confounded: therfore whatſoeuer become of the reſt, happy are they that put theyr truſt in the lord. Brother Euſebius when your argumentes be ready, let vs haue them in communicacion. I ſhall bee rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy at all tymes by Goddes grace to heare you. In the meane ſeaſon I commytte you to god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>E</speaker>
               <p>Fare ye wel brother</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo</speaker>
               <p>Wyth all my hearte.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:19"/>
            <p>Dominus mí chì adiutor nò timebo quid faciat mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. ¶P.N¶</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:1081:20"/>
            <head>The Lordes prayer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OVr father which in heauen art,</l>
               <l>And makeſt vs all one brotherhod:</l>
               <l>To call vpon thee with one heart,</l>
               <l>Our heauenly father and our god:</l>
               <l>Graunt we pray not with lyppes alone,</l>
               <l>But wyth the heart depe ſigthe and grone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy bleſſed name be ſanctifyed,</l>
               <l>Thy heauenly worde mought vs inflame</l>
               <l>In holy lyfe for to abide,</l>
               <l>To magnifie thyne holy name.</l>
               <l>From all errours defende and kepe,</l>
               <l>The litell flocke of thy pore ſhepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy kyngdome come euen at thys houre,</l>
               <l>And henceforth euerlaſtingly:</l>
               <l>Thyne holy goſt into vs power,</l>
               <l>Wyth all hys gyftes moſt plenteouſly:</l>
               <l>From Satans rage and fylthy bande,</l>
               <l>Defende vs with thy myghtie hande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy wyll be done with diligence,</l>
               <l>Lyke as in heauen in earth alſo:</l>
               <l>In trouble graunt vs pacience,</l>
               <l>And thee to obeye in wealth and woe.</l>
               <l>Let not fleſhe, bloud or any ill,</l>
               <l>Preuayle agaynſt thy holy wyll.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Geue vs thys day our dayly bread,</l>
               <l>And all other good thynges of thyne:</l>
               <l>Kepe vs from warre and from bloudeſheade,</l>
               <l>Alſo from ſickenes, dearth and pyne:</l>
               <l>That we may lyue in quietnes,</l>
               <l>Wythout all gredy carefulnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:1081:20"/>
               <l>Forgeue vs our offences all,</l>
               <l>Reliue our carefull conſcience:</l>
               <l>As we forgeue both great and ſmall,</l>
               <l>Which vnto vs haue done offence:</l>
               <l>Prepare vs lord for to ſerue thee,</l>
               <l>In perfect loue and vnitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Lord into temptacion,</l>
               <l>Leade vs not when the fynde doth rage:</l>
               <l>To wythſtande his inuaſion,</l>
               <l>Geue power and ſtrength in euery age:</l>
               <l>Arme and make ſtrong thy feable hoſte,</l>
               <l>Wyth faith and with the holy goſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Lord from euill deliuer vs,</l>
               <l>The dayes and tymes are daungerous.</l>
               <l>From euerlaſting death ſaue vs,</l>
               <l>And in our laſt neade comforte vs.</l>
               <l>A bleſſed ende to vs bequeath:</l>
               <l>Into thyne handes our ſoules receaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For thou o Lord art kyng of kynges:</l>
               <l>And thou haſt power ouer al,</l>
               <l>Thy glory ſhineth in all thynges,</l>
               <l>In the wyde world vniuerſall.</l>
               <l>Amen let it be done o Lorde,</l>
               <l>That we haue prayed with one accorde,</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
